<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Abstract of a letter from a bishop of this land sent to ___ a copie for the rest.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 3 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A23774</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A117</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21373</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12616640</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12616640</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64413</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A23774)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64413)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 339:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Abstract of a letter from a bishop of this land sent to ___ a copie for the rest.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[1], 3 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian ethics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:64413:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64413:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN ABSTRACT of a Letter from a Biſhop of this land ſent to —.</head>
            <head type="sub">A Copie for the reſt.</head>
            <p>THis Earthly Moone the Church, hath her fulls and wainings, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times her Eclipſes, whilſt the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of this ſinfull maſſe hides her beauty from the world. Whilſt ſhe wadeth in this planitary World it ſhould be vaine to expect better. It is enough when ſhe is fixed above, to be free from all change. Shee is not yet in the full of her glory. Goodneſſe repulſed gives height to ſinne; therefore have we bin worſe then our Predeceſſours, becauſe wee might have been better; becauſe there was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more light of knowledge. Turne over all Records, and Pararell ſuch helpes, ſuch care, ſuch coſt, ſuch expectation, with ſuch fruit; yet this cenſure is not confined to our Sees;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64413:2"/>and I joy not in this large ſociety, would God we were evill alone; where ſhall a man mew up himſelfe, that he may not be a witneſſe of what he would not. They are rare hands, that are free either from aſperſion of blood, or ſpots of filthineſſe, cloſe Atheiſme, ſecret Idolatry, unmercifull oppreſſion, greedy co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſſe, fymonicall ſacriledge, bloody tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, hypocriticall faſhionableneſſe, have ſpread themſelves; the Sun of peace looking upon our uncleane heape, hath bred theſe Monſters, and hath given light to this brood of darkeneſſe. If any inſult in my confeſſion, tell him that J account theſe the greateſt part of our evill, who knowes not that as the Earth is the dregs of the world, ſo <hi>Italy</hi> is the dregs of the Earth. <hi>Rome</hi> of <hi>Italy?</hi> and who doth not confeſſe to finde ſuch as our Paradice is grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous. Let them alone that will dye, and hate to be cured. Oh that remedies were as eaſie, as complaints againſt us? that we could be as ſoone cleared as convinced, that the taking of the Medicine were but ſo difficult as the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription; and yet nothing hinders us from our health but our will: Neither Goſpell, nor grace, nor glory, are ſhut up, onely our hearts are not open; yet the ſecure, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, muſt breake if they bowe not, what ſhould be done then? Except we would faine ſmart, each man amend one, and we all live.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:64413:2"/>
               <hi>Let us each of us, pull out one brand of this fire, and the flame will goe out alone.</hi> Till then, alas what availes it to talke whilſt every man cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and none of us amend, though our care begin at our ſelves it may not end there. <hi>Oh yee Sonnes of Levi, gather to your Moſes in the gate of the Campe; Conſecrate your hands to God, and ſound forth your voice like a Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet. Cry downe ſinne in earneſt, and, thunder out of that ſacred chaire of Moſes, and let your lives ſpeake yet lowder.</hi> Thus as one that delights more in amendment than excuſe, J have both cenſured and directed. So judge of my ſevere taxation. Jt ſhall be happy for us, if we can at once excuſe and diminiſh, accuſe and redreſſe iniquity. Let but the endeavour be ours, the ſucceſſe to God.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
